ACCION International Records MS196
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Center for Financial Inclusion records, 1982 -- 2008; MS196.009; 8.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains published monographs, reports, technical guides, working papers, conference proceedings, training materials, annual reports, case studies, catalogs, and correspondence that document the Center for Financial Inclusion's mission of full global financial inclusion. Launched in 2008, The Center for Financial Inclusion is an action-oriented think tank that collaborates with key industry partners to address challenges to global financial inclusion. The bulk of the materials are publications dating from 1989 to 2000 that address best practices, research, training, and policy guidance on microenterprise development worldwide. These publications were produced by ACCION International, ACCION U.S. Network, and the Center for Financial Inclusion, as well as partner organizations including the Microfinance Network, Calmeadow, and the United States Agency for International Development's Growth and Equity through Microenterprise Investments and Institutions (GEMINI) project. The GEMINI series includes a run of working papers and technical reports. Working papers runs from 2 to 50 and are missing 1, 14, 40, and 43. The technical reports run from 1-83 and are missing 1, 5, 63, 68-71, 77.
  Also of interest are course materials from a joint program between ACCION and the Harvard Business School on strategic leadership for microfinance. The course materials include annotations by Maria Otero, president and CEO of ACCION from 2000 to 2009. Files created by Cathy Quense, ACCION CFO from 1996 to 2008, include CFI publications and annual reports.
  Materials are in English, Spanish, and Portuguese.
  This material is minimally processed and in received order. Partial boxes were consolidated.
  - Publications, 1982 -- 2000; MS196.009.025 (Box 25)
  - Publications and monograph series, 1989 -- 2008; MS196.009.026 (Box 26)
  - Publications and monograph series, 1989 -- 2006; MS196.009.027 (Box 27)
  - Publications: ACCION, Microfinance Network, and GEMINI, 1992 -- 2001; MS196.009.028 (Box 28)
  - Publications: GEMINI technical reports, 1990 -- 1993; MS196.009.029 (Box 29)
  - Publications: GEMINI technical reports and working papers, 1990 -- 1993; MS196.009.030 (Box 30)
  - Publications: GEMINI publications and ACCION USA, 1984 -- 1995; MS196.009.031 (Box 31)
- Global Program records, 1985 -- 2011; MS196.010; 7.2 Linear Feet
  This series contains manuals, strategic plans, statistics, advisory reports, presentations, transparencies, guidebooks, correspondence, memoranda, meeting minutes, notes, reports, business plans, newsletters, clippings, articles, and pamphlets created by ACCION's Global Program division. Global Programs provides financial tools including microloans, business training, and other financial services to microfinance institutions (MFIs). Global Programs partners are MFIs in Latin America, the United States, China, India, and Africa. The bulk of the materials range from 1985 to 2008 and documents the development of ACCION's partnerships, primarily in Latin America and the United States.
  The subseries document many areas of interest. Partner information contains MFI information from its Latin American program partners. This includes correspondence, reports, plans, bulletins, newsletters, clippings, and articles. The bulk of the material pertains to BancoSol, the first commercial bank in the world dedicated solely to microenterprise, which ACCION helped to found in Bolivia in 1992. Training materials include manuals and programs developed by ACCION for its MFIs. An example is Dialogo de Gestiones, an educational model geared toward entrepreneurs based on modules used in Central and South America. Planning documents and presentations include information on microfinance, business plans, and proposals for its MFIs. Also of interest are Red Books, ACCION International's yearly reporting of statics, which span the years 1985 to 1997, and advisory reports of its Latin American programs, many of which pertain to Colombia.
  Files were created by Carlos Castello, head of Global Programs (2006-2016); Susana Barton, vice president and program manager (2004-2012); and Cathy Quense, ACCION CFO (1996 to 2008).
  Materials are in Spanish, English, and Portuguese.
  This material is minimally processed and arranged in 10 subseries identified by ACCION. Subseries were noted on boxes and materials were arranged into subseries accordingly. These subseries are: Partner information; Training materials; Planning documents and presentation; Red Books and statistics; Director's meetings; Memoranda of understanding; Investments; Products and services; Head of Department files; and U.S. expansion and board meetings.
  - Partner information, 1988 -- 2007; MS196.010.001; 0.0 Linear Feet
    - Partner Information: Bolivia -Dominican Republic, 1988 -- 2000; MS196.010.001.032 (Box 32)
    - Partner Information: Mexico - Peru; BancoSol, 1998 -- 2007; MS196.010.001.033; Barton, Susana (Box 33)
    - Partner Information: BancoSol, 1997 -- 2007; MS196.010.001.034 (Box 34)
  - Training materials, 1994 -- 2003; MS196.010.002; 0.0 Linear Feet
    - Training manuals, 1994 -- 2003; MS196.010.002.035 (Box 35)
    - Training manuals, 1998; MS196.010.002.036 (Box 36)
  - Planning documents and presentation, 1998 -- 2008; MS196.010.003; 7.2 Linear Feet
    - Planning documents and presentations, 1998 -- 2008; MS196.010.003.036; Barton, Susana; Castello, Carlos (Box 36)
  - Red Books and statistics, 1985 -- 1997; MS196.010.004; 7.2 Linear Feet
    - Centro ACCION Microempresarial and ACCION International, Colombia, 1991 -- 1996; MS196.010.004.037 (Box 37)
    - AITEC-Colombia, 1987 -- 1989; MS196.010.004.038 (Box 38)
    - Red Books, 1985 -- 1997; MS196.010.004.039 (Box 39)
      Missing meeting notes from 1997.
  - Director's meetings, 1994 -- 1998; MS196.010.005; 7.2 Linear Feet
    - Director's meetings, 1994 -- 1998; MS196.010.005.039 (Box 39)
  - Memoranda of understanding, 2000 -- 2005; MS196.010.006; 7.2 Linear Feet
    - Memoranda of understanding, 2000 -- 2005; MS196.010.006.039 (Box 39)
  - Investments, 1996 -- 2008; MS196.010.007; 7.2 Linear Feet
    - Investments, 1996 -- 2008; MS196.010.007.039 (Box 39)
    - Investments, 1998 -- 1999; MS196.010.007.040 (Box 40)
  - Products and services, 1998 -- 2001; MS196.010.008; 7.2 Linear Feet
    - Products and services, 1998 -- 2001; MS196.010.008.040; Castello, Carlos (Box 40)
  - Head of Department files, 1998 -- 2000; MS196.010.009; 7.2 Linear Feet
    - Head of department files, 1998 -- 2000; MS196.010.009.040; Castello, Carlos (Box 40)
  - US expansion and board meetings, 1990 -- 2011; MS196.010.010; 7.2 Linear Feet
    - ACCION USA-Working Capital merger, 1993 -- 2003; MS196.010.010.031 (Box 31)
    - ACCION USA expansion, 1998 -- 2011; MS196.010.010.040; Quense, Cathy (Box 40)
    - Financial committees and board meetings, 1997 -- 2008; MS196.010.010.041; Quense, Cathy (Box 41)
    - Finance and planning, 1990 -- 2008; MS196.010.010.042; Quense, Cathy (Box 42)
    - Board meetings and task forces, 1994 -- 2009; MS196.010.010.043; Quense, Cathy (Box 43)
- Administrative records, 1993 -- 2012; 1993 -- 2008; MS196.011; 1.3 Linear Feet; 123 Megabytes; 34 Digital Object(s)
  This series contains organizational preparedness and disaster planning documents, emergency contact information, legal documents, management meeting minutes, and other records pertaining to the operation and administrative activities of ACCION International. The bulk of the materials date from approximately 1993 to 2008. Of particular note are planning documents relating to ACCION International's 2001 move of their offices in Somerville and Cambridge to Roland Street in Boston. Many of the files in this series were created by Cathy Quense, chief financial officer (CFO) (1984-2009).
  This series is restricted for 75 years from date of creation, due to privacy concerns.
  This series is arranged in received order. Materials from the files of Cathy Quense were arranged at the end of the series.
  - Administrative records, 1993 -- 2008; MS196.011.090 (Box 90)
  - Monthly management reports, 2010 -- 2012; MS196.002834; 123 Megabytes; 34 Digital Object(s)
    Contains monthly reports for senior management pertaining to communications, events, finance, human resources, investments, operations, and resource development.
  - A Working Guide to ACCION International draft, 1997 June 09; MS196.002842 (Box 98, Folder 3)
- Strategic planning records, 1993 -- 2005; 1994 -- 2005; MS196.012; 8.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains strategic planning documents, including drafts, correspondence, and notes. The materials in this series date from approximately 1994 to 2005.
  The strategic plans describe the mission and goals for ACCION International on a near-term basis, usually three to four years, and serve as a guidebook for staff. The documents discuss ACCION's focus as an organization, and include suggestions for becoming more effective and efficient. The plans were developed with input from staff at all levels, but particularly members of senior management. Many of the strategic plans are drafts labeled with the note "Confidential: For Internal Distribution Only."
  Files in Box 090 were created by Cathy Quense, chief financial officer (1984-2009).
  This series is restricted for 20 years from date of creation.
  This series is arranged in received order.
  - Strategic planning records, 1993 -- 2005; MS196.012.048 (Box 48)
  - Strategic planning records: Cathy Quense files, 1994 -- 2005; MS196.012.090; Quense, Cathy (Box 90)
- Conference records, 1984 -- 1999; MS196.013; 7.2 Linear Feet
  This series contains agendas, lists of participants, conference proceedings, and conference notes. The bulk of the material ranges from 1987 to 1999 and represents an internal annual conference for ACCION directors. These conferences occurred all over the world and participants included directors of ACCION, its partner members, and invited speakers. This conference provided an opportunity for departments to present, plan, and to hold workshops on topical items. The name of this conference varied over time, from the Conferencia de Personal in the 1980s, to the Conferencia de Directores from the early 1990s on, to Conferencia de Directores de la Red ACCION beginning in 1999.
  Also represented in this series is the Microfinance Network conference, with participants from several microfinance companies. Conference topics include tapping into capital markets, working with investors, incentives for information technology staff, and innovations in rural finance. Other conference materials may be found in Series 006, Communications and External Affairs records.
  This material is minimally processed and arranged in received order, which is roughly chronological.
  - Conference proceedings, 1984 -- 1999; MS196.013.048; Quense, Cathy (Box 48)
- Websites, 2013 -- 2019; MS196.002830; 2 Web sites
  This series is open for research.
  A collection of 2 websites crawled by DCA to document the presence of Accion on the web. The websites in this series are crawled on an annual basis.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Archived websites can be viewed online using the Internet Archive's Wayback Machine.
  - Accion | Investing in Individuals. Improving our World., 2013-04-12 -- 2019-10-24; MS196.002831; 1 Web sites
  - Center for Financial Inclusion, 2014-10-24 -- 2019-10-24; MS196.002832; 1 Web sites